<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="Amadis.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amadis of Gaul, by VASCO LOBEJRA.</title>
            <editor role="translator">Robert Southey</editor>
            <editor>Stacey Triplette</editor>
            <editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority ana="printer">Printed by N. Biggs, Cross-court, Fleet-street</authority>
            <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Paternoster Row, London</pubPlace>
            <date>1803</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Rekeyed from a public domain Google-digitized text via HathiTrust.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="S21">
            <head>Chapter 21. <locus from="189" to="194"/>
            </head>

            <p>
               <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c1"/>
               <s>Such speed made <persName ref="#Arcalaus">Arcalaus</persName> in the armour and on
                  the horse of him whom he had enchanted, that on the tenth day he met <persName
                     ref="#Lisuarte">King Lisuarte</persName> riding abroad in the morning to take
                  the air,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c2"/>accompanied with a great train.<anchor
                     ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c5"/>They seeing the horse and arms <anchor
                     ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c5"/>of <persName ref="#Amadis"
                     >Amadis</persName>
                  <anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c7"/>were greatly rejoiced, and rode on to
                  welcome him<anchor ana="end"/>; <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c8"/>but coming
                  nearer, they saw that it was not he for whom they looked,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c9"/> for Arcalaus had his head and hands
                  unarmed, and they were greatly amazed.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c10"/>Arcalaus came before the King and said,
                     <anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c11"/>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Arcalaus"/>I come, Sir, to acquit a
                  promise wherein I stand bound, to let you understand how I have slain a Knight in
                  battle.</s>
               <s>And albeit I must be content to declare mine own praise, which were more
                  honourable for me being reported by another in mine absence,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c12"/>yet am I constrained to do no less, for
                  the covenant was between me and him whom I have slain, <anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c13"/>that the conqueror should cut off the
                  other's head,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c14"/> and present himself before you as this
                     day.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c15"/>
                  <!-- st 8.26.15 all inside c.15 but Southey reverses the order -->If he slew me, I
                  told him it was Arcalaus whom he would slay; and much was I grieved when he said
                  he was the Queen's Knight <anchor ana="end"/>, <anchor ana="start"
                     synch="#M20_p1_c16"/>and by name Amadis of Gaul.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c17"/>In this guise came he to his
                     death,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c18"/> and I remain with the honour of the
                     battle.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
            </p>
            <p resp="#Southey">
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c19"/>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Lisuarte"/>Holy Mary!<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="intStart"/> exclaimed the King,<milestone unit="said"
                     ana="intEnd"/> is the best Knight in the world slain?<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c21"/>and with that they all began to
                     lament.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c21.1"/>But Arcalaus turned back by the way he
                  came, and all cursed him and besought God that he might speedily die an evil
                     death,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c22"/>which they with their own swords would at
                  once have given him but for his own tale,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" type="add"/> how Amadis was slain in an accorded
                     battle.<anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
            </p>
            <p resp="#Southey">
               <s>
                  <anchor ana="start" type="add"/>Forthwith <anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c23"/> the King returned in heavy
                  affliction.</s>
               <s>The news spread <anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c24"/>and reached the Queen's house,<anchor
                     ana="end"/><anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c26"/> and she and all her Ladies
                  lamented, for greatly was Amadis beloved by all;<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" type="add"/>but<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c27"/><persName ref="#Oriana">Oriana</persName>
                  hearing their lamentation sent the <persName ref="#Damsel_Denmark">Damsel of
                     Denmark</persName> to enquire its cause,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c28"/>who presently returned beating her
                     face,<anchor ana="end"/>
                  <anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c29"/>and with a wild cry looked at
                  Oriana.</s><anchor ana="end"/>
               <s><anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c30"/>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Damsel_Denmark"/>Ah, Lady! what a
                  grief--what a misery!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>So that Oriana trembled from head to foot, and exclaimed, <anchor ana="end"
                     /><anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c31"/><milestone unit="said" ana="start"
                     resp="#Oriana"/>Holy Virgin, if Amadis should be dead!<milestone unit="said"
                     ana="end"/><anchor ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s><anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c32"/>The Damsel answered, <milestone
                     unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Damsel_Denmark"/>ah me, he is dead!<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="end"/> and with that Oriana's heart died away within her, and
                  she fell.<anchor ana="end"/></s>
               <s><anchor ana="start" synch="#M20_p1_c33"/>Then ran the Damsel to <persName
                     ref="#Mabilia">Mabilia</persName><anchor ana="end"/><anchor ana="start"
                     synch="#M20_p1_c34"/> tearing her hair, <anchor ana="end"/><anchor ana="start"
                     synch="#M20_p1_c35"/><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Damsel_Denmark"
                  />help, help, for my Lady is dying.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/><anchor ana="end"/><!-- st stopped here> -->
               </s>
               <s>Mabilia, though her own grief was so great that greater none could be, yet not for
                  that did she neglect what remedy might profit; she took the Princess in her arms,
                  and poured<note anchored="true" resp="#Southey">The <bibl corresp="#Munday"
                        >English translation</bibl> says, she unlaced her garments to give her more
                     liberty, and bathed her temples and pulses with vinegar and cold water.</note>
                  cold water on her face, and bade the Damsel fasten the door of the chamber, that
                  none might see her in that passion.</s>
               <s>She recovering her senses, exclaimed, <milestone unit="said" ana="start"
                     resp="#Oriana"/>Ah friends, let me die and be at rest: why would ye make me so
                  faithless that I should live even an hour after him! What though his dwelling be
                  in the cold earth, where all love ceaseth, yet greater shall be our loves when in
                  the other world we are united!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> and then again
                  she swooned; her long hair hanging to the ground, her hands clenched upon her
                  breast that Mabilia thought she was indeed dead, and cried, <milestone unit="said"
                     ana="start" resp="#Mabilia"/>Oh God! let me die also, since they whom I loved
                  best are gone.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Damsel_Denmark"/>For God's sake, dear
                  Lady, <milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>quoth the Damsel,<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="intEnd"/> let not your good sense fail you now, when it is so
                     needed.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>Roused by these words Mabilia recovered herself; they placed Oriana in bed, and
                  poured water again upon her face and upon her breast, so that she revived.</s>
               <s>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Mabilia"/>Take heart,<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="intStart"/> said Mabilia,<milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>
                  and do not so readily believe such tidings; that Knight may have borrowed the arms
                  of Amadis, or stolen them: who shall vouch for his truth?</s>
               <milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               <s>But Oriana had fixed her eyes upon the window where first she talked with Amadis,
                  and in a faint and feeble voice exclaimed, <milestone unit="said" ana="start"
                     resp="#Oriana"/>how bitter is the remembrance that thou excitest! long as thou
                  shalt last, never will two others discourse in thee with such pure and perfect
                     truth!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Mabilia"/>Think you, <milestone
                     unit="said" ana="intStart"/>said Mabilia,<milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>
                  that if I believed his death I should have power to comfort you?<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="end"/> and thus with such consolation all that day they strove
                  to cheer her who would not be comforted; and the night was worse than the day, and
                  oftentimes they feared that she would never see the morning.</s>
               <s>But the next day, at the hour when they were about to lay the napkins before the
                  King, Brandoyuas entered the palace, leading <persName ref="#Grindalaya"
                     >Grindalaya</persName>, and they both went and knelt before the King.</s>
               <s>He who greatly esteemed him, and had been troubled for his long absence, enquired
                  where he had tarried.</s>
               <s>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Brandoivas"/>Sir, said he, in a dungeon,
                  whence I should never have come out, but for the good Knight Amadis, who delivered
                  me and this Lady, and many others, doing there such deeds of arms as only he could
                  have atchieved.</s>
               <s>And he would there have been slain by the worst treason that ever was known, by
                  the traitor Arcalaus, if two Damsels had not helped him, who surely must not a
                  little have loved him.</s>
               <milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               <s>Lisuarte at this, rose instantly from table;<milestone unit="said" ana="start"
                     resp="#Lisuarte"/>--tell me, my friend, by the faith which you owe to God and
                  to me, is Amadis alive?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>
               </s>
               <s>
                  <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Brandoivas"/>By that faith, <milestone
                     unit="said" ana="intStart"/>replied Brandoyvas,<milestone unit="said"
                     ana="intEnd"/> I left him alive and well not ten days ago!<milestone
                     unit="said" ana="end"/> Then was there such joy that greater could not be.</s>
               <s>The King sent Grindalaya to <persName ref="#Brisena">Brisena</persName>, and well
                  was she welcomed for her tidings.</s>
               <s>The Damsel of Denmark soon heard it, and hastened to Oriana, and restored her from
                  death to life; and Mabilia sent for Grindalaya that they might hear the whole from
                  her own mouth, and the Princesses would suffer her to eat no where but at their
                  own table, that she might relate it more at length.</s>
               <s>On her return to the Queen's apartment, she found <persName ref="#Arban">King
                     Arban of North Wales</persName>, who dearly loved her.</s>
               <s>Then was there such joy as cannot be expressed; and King Arban told Brisena how
                  she was daughter to King Ardroyd of Serolys; and Brisena, as well for her high
                  rank as for the good tidings she had brought, besought her to remain in her court;
                  to the which she was nothing loth.</s>
               <s>Brisena also sent for Grindalaya's sister, Aldeva: this was she who was the friend
                  of Galaor, and for whose sake he had been so persecuted by the Dwarf.</s>
               <s>So there were great rejoicings in the court of King Lisuarte.</s>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
