<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="Amadis.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amadis of Gaul, by VASCO LOBEJRA.</title>
            <editor role="translator">Robert Southey</editor>
            <editor>Stacey Triplette</editor>
            <editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority ana="printer">Printed by N. Biggs, Cross-court, Fleet-street</authority>
            <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Paternoster Row, London</pubPlace>
            <date>1803</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Rekeyed from a public domain Google-digitized text via HathiTrust.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="S1">
            <head>Chapter 1. <locus from="1" to="8"/></head>
            <!--ebb: 2015-08-05: Okay, we have to use <p> as the base structural unit of any prose text in TEI, 
               so we'll have to make each chapter be a single long paragraph in Montalvo. 
               We'll use the <milestone/> element in the Southey text to indicate his imposed paragraph breaks within that.
            A <milestone/> element appears at the beginning of each of Southey's paragraphs.
            -->
            <!--ebb: 2015-08-20: I'm now rethinking this use of milestone, since we've discovered occasional paragraph breaks within chapters in Montalvo. I'm just going to wrap paragraphs in the <p> element the way the TEI intended! 
                  Perhaps the <s> elements and <cl> elements don't really need to be sitting in the same hierarchical positions in the file anyway, since we are using <milestone/> markers to stitch the Southey together with units of the Montalvo text.-->
            <p><s>Not many years after the passion of our Redeemer there was a Christian King in the
                  lesser Britain, by name <persName ref="#Garinter">Garinter</persName>, who being in the law of truth, was of much
                  devotion and good ways.</s><s>This King had two Daughters by a noble Lady his
                  wife.</s><s>The eldest was married to <persName ref="#Languines">Languines King of Scotland</persName>; she was called
                     <persName ref="#Guirnalda">the Lady of the Garland</persName>, because her husband taking great pleasure to behold her
                  beautiful tresses, would have them covered only with a chaplet of
                  flowers.</s><s><persName ref="#Agrajes">Agrayes</persName> and <persName ref="#Mabilia">Mabilia</persName> were their children, a Knight and Damsel of
                  whom in this history much mention is made.</s><s><persName ref="#Helisena">Elisena</persName> the other daughter was
                  far more beautiful, and although she had been demanded in marriage by many great
                  Princes, yet she would wed with none, but for her solitary and holy life was
                  commonly called the Lost Devotee<note anchored="true" resp="#Southey">La Beata
                     perdida. <hi rend="italic">Methodist, Puritan,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">the
                        Elect,</hi> would perhaps express the meaning of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Beata,</hi> which is in common use, if they were not sectarian
                     words.</note>, because it was considered that for one of such rank, gifted with
                  such beauty and sought in marriage by so many chiefs, this way of life was not
                  fitting.</s></p>
            <p><s>King Garinter who was somewhat striken in years, took delight in hunting.</s><s>It
                  happened one day, that having gone from his <placeName ref="#Alima">town of Alima</placeName> to the chace, and being
                  separated from his people, as he went along the forest saying his prayers, he saw
                  to the left a brave battle of one Knight against two.</s><s>Soon had he knowledge
                  of the twain, in that they were his own vassals, who being proud men and of
                  powerful lineage had often by their evil customs offended him.</s><s>Who the third
                  was he knew not, but not relying so much in the worth of the one, as he feared the
                  two, he drew aside and waited the event, which sorted to such effect, as by the
                  hand of that one the others were both slain.</s><s>This done <persName ref="#Perion">the Stranger</persName> came
                  towards the King, and seeing him alone, said, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>Gentle Sir, what country is this
                  wherein Knights Errant are thus assailed?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>The King replied, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Garinter"/>Marvel not at
                  this, Knight, for our Country yields as others do, both good and bad: as for these
                  men, they have often offended, even against their Lord and King, who could do no
                  justice upon them, because of their kindred, and also because they harboured in
                  this covered mountain.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s></p>
            <p><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/><s>This King you speak of, replied <persName ref="#Perion">the Stranger</persName>, I come to seek him from a far land,
                  and bring him tidings from a dear friend.</s><s>If you know where he may be found,
                     I pray you tell me.</s><milestone unit="said" ana="end"/><s>The King answered, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Garinter"/>Befall what may, I shall not fail to
                        speak what is true.</s><s>I am the King.</s><milestone unit="said" ana="end"/><s>The Knight then loosing his shield
                  and helmet gave them to his Squire, and went to embrace Garinter, saying that he
                  was King Perion of Gaul who had long desired to know him.</s><s>Greatly were these
                  Kings contented that their meeting was in such a manner, and conferring together
                  they took their way through the wood towards the city, when suddenly a Hart ran
                  before them which had escaped the toils.</s><s>They followed at full speed,
                  thinking to kill it, but a Lion springing from a thicket before them, seized the
                  Hart, and having torn it open with his mighty claws, stood fiercely looking at the
                  Kings.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>Fierce as you are<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, said King Perion,<milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/> you shall leave us part of the
                     game!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> and he took his arms and alighted from his horse, who being affrighted at
                  the wild beast would not go near him, and placing his shield before him went
                  towards the Lion sword in hand.</s><s>The Lion left his prey and came against him,
                  they closed, and Perion at the moment when he was under the beast and in most
                  danger, thrust his sword into his belly.</s><s>When Garinter saw him fall, he said
                  within himself not without cause is that Knight famed to be the best in the
                  world.</s><s>Meanwhile their train came up, and then was their prey and venison
                  laid on two horses and carried to the City.</s></p>
            <p><s>The Queen being advised of her guest they found the palace richly adorned, and the
                  tables covered.</s><s>At the highest the Kings seated themselves: at the other
                  sate the Queen with Elisena her daughter, and there were they served, as in the
                  house of such a man beseemed.</s><s>Then being in that solace, as that Princess
                  was so beautiful and King Perion on his part equal, in that hour and point they so
                  regarded each other, that her great modesty and holy life could not now avail, but
                  that she was taken with great and incurable love; and the King in like manner,
                  though till then his heart had been free, so that during the meal both the one and
                  the other appeared absent in thought.</s><s>When the tables were removed, the
                  Queen would depart to her chamber; Elisena rising dropt a ring from her lap, which
                  she had taken off when she wash'd her hands, and in her confusion of mind
                  forgotten.</s><s>She stooped for it and Perion who was near her stooped also, so
                  that their hands met, and he taking her hand prest it.</s><s>She coloured deeply
                     and thanked the King for his service.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>Ah, Lady, said he, it shall not be the
                        last, for all my life shall be spent in your service.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s></p>
            <p><s>She followed her mother, but so disturbed that her sight was dizzy, and now not
                  able to endure her feelings she went and discovered them to the damsel <persName ref="#Darioleta">Darioleta</persName>
                  in whom she confided, and with tears from her eyes and from her heart, besought
                  her to find out if King Perion loved any other woman.</s><s>Darioleta suprized at
                  this alteration, pitied and comforted her mistress, and went to King Perion's
                  chamber.</s><s>She found his <persName ref="#Squire1">Squire</persName> at the door with the King's garments which he
                     was about to give him; <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>friend<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, said she<milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>, go you about your other affairs, for I
                     must wait upon your master<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>The Squire, thinking it was the custom of the
                  country, gave her the garments and went away.</s><s>She then entered the chamber
                  where the King was in bed.</s><s>He, who had seen her converse with Elisena
                  confidently, now hoped that she might bring some remedy to his passion, and said
                  to her all in trembling, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>fair friend, what demand ye?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>I bring you wherewith
                     to cloathe yourself<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>, she replied.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>That should be for my heart<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, said Perion,
                        <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>which is now stript and naked of all my joy<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>As how?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> said the
                           Damsel.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>Thus<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, quoth he,<milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/> coming into this land with entire liberty, and
                  apprehending nothing but the chance of arms, here in this house I have been
                  wounded by a mortal wound, for which if you fair Damsel, can procure me remedy,
                  you shall be well recompensed<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>He then charged her not to discover him but
                  where it was requisite, and told her his love for Elisena.</s><s>Then said
                     Darioleta, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>my Lord, promise me on the faith of a King and a Knight, that you will
                  take to wife my Lady Elisena, when time shall serve, and right soon will I bring
                  ye, where not only your heart shall be satisfied, but hers also, who, it may be,
                  is in as much or more thought and dolour than you, with the same wound.</s><s>But
                     without this promise you shall never win her.</s><milestone unit="said" ana="end"/><s>The King whose will was
                  already disposed by God that that which ensued might come to pass, took his sword
                  which was by him, and laying his right hand upon the cross of its hilt, pronounced
                  these words, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>I swear by this Cross, and this Sword wherewith I received the order
                  of Knighthood, to perform whatever you shall require for the Lady
                  Elisena<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>Be you then of good cheer<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, said she, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>for I also will effect my
                     promise<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s></p>
            <p><s>Darioleta returned to the Princess and told her how she had sped; <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>you know, said
                  she, that in the chamber where King Perion lodgeth there is a door opening to the
                  garden, whence your father used to go out, and which at this present is covered
                  with the hangings; but I have the key thereof, and we can go in at night, when all
                  in the palace are at rest<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>When Elisena heard this she was highly contented,
                     but recollecting herself, she replied, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Helisena"/>how shall this be brought to pass, seeing
                     that my father will lodge in the chamber with King Perion?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>Leave that to me
                        <milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>said the Damsel, and with that they parted.</s></p>
            <p><s>When it was night Darioleta drew aside the <persName ref="#Squire1">Squire of Perion</persName>, and asked him if he
               was of gentle birth.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Squire1"/>Aye, said he, the son of a Knight! but why ask ye?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>for
                  the desire I have, quoth she, to know one thing, which I beseech you by the faith
                  you owe to God and to the King your master, not to hide from me.</s><s>Who is the
                     Lady whom your Master loveth best?</s><milestone unit="said" ana="end"/><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Squire1"/>My Master<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>, replied the Squire, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>loves all
                        in general, and none as you mean<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>While they thus talked Garinter came nigh,
                  who seeing Darioleta in conference with Perion's Squire, called her and asked what
                  he had to say to her.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>In sooth my Lord, <milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/>quoth she, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>he tells me that his
                  Master is wont to be alone, and certainly I think he will feel himself embarrassed
                  by your company<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>Garinter hearing that went to King Perion and said, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Garinter"/>My Lord
                  I have many affairs to settle, and must rise at the hour of matins, and that you
                  may not be disturbed, you had better be alone in your chamber.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>King Perion
                     replied, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>do as shall seem best to your liking<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>Then Garinter understood that
                  Darioleta had told him rightly of his guest's inclination, and ordered his bed to
                  be removed from Perion's apartment.</s><s>These tidings Darioleta carried to her
                  mistress, and they waited the hour when all should retire to sleep.</s></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
