<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Site Index for the Amadis Project</title>
            <author>Stacey Triplette</author>
            <author>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</author>
            <author>Helena Bermúdez Sabel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="historical_people">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="st">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Triplette</surname>
                     <forename>Stacey</forename>
                     <roleName>Editor</roleName>
                  </persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="ebb">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Beshero-Bondar</surname>
                     <forename>Elisa</forename>
                     <roleName>Editor</roleName>
                  </persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="heb">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Bermúdez Sabel</surname>
                     <forename>Helena</forename>
                     <roleName>Editor</roleName>
                  </persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Southey">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Southey</surname>
                     <forename>Robert</forename>
                     <roleName>Translator</roleName>
                  </persName>
                  <persName>Bob Southey</persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Montalvo">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Rodríguez de Montalvo</surname>
                     <forename>Garci</forename>
                     <roleName>Editor-Compiler of 1508</roleName>
                  </persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Lobeira">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>de
                        Lobeira<!-- st 8.6.15 When we have a Spanish surname with a de or de la, put the de in front of the capitalized part of the last name, i.e. de Montalvo, not Montalvo, de --></surname>
                     <forename>Vasco</forename>
                     <roleName>Apocryphal Author</roleName>
                  </persName>



               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </div>
         <div type="fictional_characters">
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="Arthur">
                  <persName>King Arthur</persName>
                  <!--ebb 2015-09-14: I'm not sure this entry is necessary, but I'm adding it just in case he comes up again later.-->
                  <note resp="#ebb">Not a central character, but referenced as a great historical deliverer, repealing
                  unjust laws such as the edict of death to a woman pregnant out of wedlock.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Floyon">
                  <!--ebb 2015-09-14: I'm not sure this entry is necessary, but I'm adding it just in case he comes up again later.-->
                  <persName>Floyon</persName>
                  <note resp="#ebb">Not a central character. <persName ref="#Arthur">King Arthur</persName> revoked the law condemning unwed mothers to death when he defeated Floyon.</note>
               </person>
              
               <person xml:id="Brisena">
                  <persName>Brisena</persName>
<note resp="#ebb">a Queen, apparently ruling in Windsor.</note>
               </person>


               <person xml:id="Damsel_Denmark">
                  <persName>Damsel of Denmark</persName>
                  <persName>doncella de Denamarca</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">The Damsel of Denmark is Oriana's personal attendant, associated
                     with her mother Brisena who is originally from Denmark. The Damsel of Denmark
                     is unique in that she has no first name. Her brother is the messenger Durin. In
                     Book III she loses Oriana's illegitimate infant Esplandian to a lioness.
                  </note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Helisena">
                  <persName>Helisena</persName>
                  <persName>Elisena</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Helisena is Amadis of Gaul's mother and the daughter of King
                     Garinter. She and Perion of Gaul indulged in a clandestine liaison in the first
                     chapters of Book I (debateably a clandestine marriage). She later celebrates a
                     public marriage to Perion and has two more children, Galaor and Melicia.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Perion">
                  <persName>Perión de Gaula</persName>
                  <persName>Perion of Gaul</persName>
                  <persName>Perión</persName>
                  <persName>Perion</persName>
                  <note resp="st">Perion of Gaul is Amadis of Gaul's father. He and Helisena indulge
                     in a clandestine liaison (debateably a clandestine marriage) early in Book I
                     and later marry. They have two other children, Galaor and Melicia. Perion makes
                     clear that he considers Amadis legitimate by naming him heir over his younger
                     brother Galaor. Perion fights in Lisuarte of Britain's wars and in his grandson
                     Esplandian's campaign at Constantinople in Montalvo's sequel, where he dies.
                     Amadis succeeds to the throne of Britain on Perion's death.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Darioleta">
                  <persName>Darioleta</persName>
                  <note resp="st">Darioleta is Helisena's maid. In Book I she helps Helisena hide
                     her pregnancy and constructs the ark in which the infant Amadis floats down the
                     river. She writes a note declaring the child's name, covers it in wax, and
                     places it in the ark. In later episodes she and her family are imprisoned by
                     Arcalaus and then by the giant Balan. Balan kills her son in combat, but after
                     Amadis brokers a peace, Darioleta's daughter marries the giant's son Bravor and
                     starts a new lineage of Christianized half-giants.</note>

               </person>
               <person xml:id="Garinter">
                  <persName>Garínter</persName>
                  <persName>Garinter</persName>
                  <note resp="st">Garinter, king of Little Britain, is the father of Helisena and
                     her sister, the Lady of the Garland. After his death the Lady of the Garland's
                     husband, King Languines of Scotland, inherits his kingdom.</note>

               </person>
               <person xml:id="Gandales">
                  <persName>Gandales</persName>
                  <note resp="st">Gandales is the knight of Scotland who finds the infant Amadis in
                     the ark. He raises Amadis until the age of six and then sends him, reluctantly,
                     to the court of Languines. Gandales's son Gandalin is Amadis's squire and
                     lifelong friend. Gandales should not be confused with the similarly named
                     Galvanes Lackland (Galvanes Sin Tierra), Agrayes's uncle, or the giant
                     Gandalaz.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Languines">
                  <persName>Languines</persName>
                  <note resp="st">The king of Scotland, Languines is married to Amadis's aunt, the
                     Lady of the Garland. He is the father of Agrayes and Mabilia. Amadis, Oriana
                     and Gandalin are fostered at his court in their youth.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Urganda">
                  <persName>Urganda</persName>
                  <persName>Urganda la desconocida</persName>
                  <persName>Urganda the unknown</persName>
                  <note resp="st">Urganda is the good sorceress who helps Amadis in the style of the
                     Lady of the Lake. Her magic gives her the ability to know the future, to change
                     her appearance, and to bewitch others. In one instance one of her spells nearly
                     causes a woman to drown herself because it made the victim feel as though she
                     were on fire. The Urganda of Book I resembles typical fairy characters: she is
                     vindictive, she entraps a human lover, and she protects her favorite people and
                     punishes others with magic. From Book II onward Urganda becomes an increasingly
                     benevolent source of deus ex machina and performs only good deeds, primarily
                     deeds of prophecy. She tends to send her predictions by letter.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Arcalaus">
                  <persName>Arcalaus</persName>
                  <persName>Arcalaus the Enchanter</persName>
                  <persName>Arcaláus</persName>
                  <persName>Arcaláus el encantador</persName>
                  <note resp="#st"> Arcalaus the enchanter is Amadis's nemesis and an enemy of
                     Lisuarte. He imprisons Amadis by enchantment in Book I and tries to convince
                     Lisuarte's court that he has killed the young knight in battle. Later he
                     attempts to abduct Oriana to marry her to his son. He imprisons Amadis and
                     Gandalin again in Book III. Urganda urges them to save his life.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Lisuarte">
                  <persName>Lisuarte</persName>
                  <persName>King Lisuarte</persName>
                  <persName>el rey Lisuarte</persName>
                  <note resp="#st"> Lisuarte is the king of Britain during the bulk of Amadís I-IV.
                     He has two daughters, Oriana and Leonoreta, and a wife, Brisena. During the
                     early portion of Amadís Book I Lisuarte is represented as a good and fair king,
                     both a literal and metaphorical ancestor for Arthur. Like Arthur he gathers
                     virtuous knights to his court. As the books progress Lisuarte becomes the
                     stereotype of the bad king, tyrannical, cruel, and melancholic. He values the
                     truth of his word but breaks promises to his elder daughter Oriana,
                     disinheriting her in Book III for her younger sister and attempting to force
                     her to marry el Patín (the Gosling), the incompetent emperor of Rome. In Book
                     IV Lisuarte becomes entrapped by an enchantress while hunting; his grandson
                     Esplandián will save him in the sequel volume <bibl>Las Sergas de Esplandián
                        (The Exploits of Esplandián)</bibl>. </note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Amadis">
                  <persName>Amadís</persName>
                  <persName>Amadís de Gaula</persName>
                  <persName>Amadis</persName>
                  <persName>Amadis of Gaul</persName>
                  <persName>Amadis of Gaule</persName>
                  <persName>Amadis de Gaule</persName>
                  <persName>Amadís Sin Tiempo</persName>
                  <persName>Donzel del mar</persName>
                  <persName>Child of the Sea</persName>
                  <persName>Beltenebros</persName>
                  <persName>Caballero de la Verde Espada</persName>
                  <persName>Knight of the Green Sword</persName>
                  <note resp="#st"> Amadis of Gaul (Amadís de Gaula), son of Perion of Gaul and
                     Elisena of Scotland, was abandoned at birth and set to float, Moses-like, in an
                     arc down a river. He was raised by Gandales of Scotland and as a young child
                     went to serve at the court of his uncle, king Languines of Scotland. There he
                     meets Oriana, also Languines's ward. He becomes a knight at age fifteen.
                     Coincidence allows his father Perion to be the one to knight him, but the
                     monarchs of Gaul do not discover their eldest son's identity until after
                     Amadis's duel with king Abies of Ireland. Amadis is known as the Child of the
                     Sea (Donzel del mar) in the early books, then Amadis when he recovers his name,
                     Beltenebros during his estrangement from Oriana, and the Knight of the Green
                     Sword when he travels to Romania and Constantinople. Amadis has two brothers,
                     illegitimate elder brother Florestan and younger brother Galaor, and a sister,
                     Melicia. He becomes king of Britain and Gaul in the fifth volume of Amadis, Las
                     Sergas de Esplandián. Like Lancelot, Amadis is the best knight in the world
                     until his son replaces him in that role. In the medieval, primitive versions of
                     the legend Amadis is thought to have perished in a duel with Esplandian; the
                     two battled without recognizing each other. In Montalvo's version (the 1508 and
                     all later texts) Amadis survives to marry Oriana, have more children, and rule
                     two kingdoms.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Oriana">
                  <persName>Oriana</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Oriana is the daughter of Lisuarte and Brisena, the heiress
                     apparent to the throne of Britain. She becomes a ward of King Languines of
                     Scotland at ten years old and meets Amadis, then known as the Child of the Sea
                     (Donzel del mar). Amadis soon declares himself her knight, and in secret, their
                     love grows. Oriana rules their relationship, giving Amadis permission to go on
                     adventures or alternately restricting him. They consummate their
                     relationship--by Oriana's decision, not Amadis's--when he saves her from
                     Arcalaus. In Book II Oriana becomes jealous when she believes that Amadis has
                     had a liaison with rival princess Briolania. She writes a letter of dismissal
                     that causes Amadís to fall into a state of love-madness during which he nearly
                     dies of grief. During this phase of the text Amadis is known as Beltenebros.
                     Amadis and Oriana reconcile and have a child together, Esplandian. Whether
                     their liaison counts as a clandestine marriage or is merely illicit is a
                     subject of critical debate. The Oriana of the primitive or medieval Amadis
                     throws herself from a tower when she learns of Amadis's death; the Oriana of
                     the 1508 survives to marry Amadis, become queen of Britain and Gaul, and have
                     more children.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Mabilia">
                  <persName>Mabilia</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">The daughter of Languines of Scotland, sister of Amadis's
                     companion Agrayes and Amadis's first cousin, Mabilia serves Oriana as her most
                     honored lady-in-waiting. Efficient and no-nonsense, she helps conceal Amadis
                     and Oriana's love affair, which could prove fatal to Oriana if discovered. She
                     comforts Oriana in times of trouble, helps hide the infant Esplandian, and
                     writes letters to her cousin Amadis with messages from Oriana. Mabilia marries
                     Grasandor in Book IV as part of the collective wedding Amadis arranges.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Brandoivas">
                  <persName>Brandoivas</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">A minor knight, Brandoivas serves Lisuarte's court, carrying
                     messages and providing information.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Grindalaya">
                  <persName>Grindalaya</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">A minor noblewoman, Grindalaya is the lover of King Arban of
                     North Wales, himself a minor character associated with Lisuarte's court. Aldeva
                     is her sister.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Aldeva">
                  <persName>Aldeva</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Aldeva, a minor female character, is Galaor's lover in Book I.
                     Grindalaya is her sister.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Arban">
                  <persName>Arban of North Wales</persName>
                  <persName>Arbán de Norgales</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Arban is a minor knight, a sometime companion of Amadis who is
                     associated with Lisuarte's court. Grindalaya is his lover.</note>
               </person>

               <person xml:id="Guirnalda">
                  <persName>dueña de la Guirnalda</persName>
                  <persName>Lady of the Garland</persName>
                  <note resp="#heb">Oldest daughter of Garinter, king of Little Britain. She is
                     called the Lady of the Garland, because her husband, King Languines of
                     Scotland, never allowed her to cover her hair but with a chaplet of
                     flowers.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Agrajes">
                  <persName>Agrajes</persName>
                  <persName>Agrayes</persName>
                  <note resp="#heb">Son of Languines of Scotland. He is Amadis's companion and first
                     cousin as well as a great knight in his own right. He is in love with Olinda la
                     mesurada, a princess of Norway.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Squire1">
                  <note resp="#heb">Perion's unnamed squire. He assists in the clandestine meetings
                     between Helisena and his master.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Briolanja">
                  <persName>Briolanja</persName>
                  <persName>la reina de Sobradisa</persName>
                  <persName>Briolania</persName>
                  <persName>queen of Sobradisa</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Briolanja is first introduced as "la niña hermosa," the beautiful
                     child of the betrayed king of Sobradisa. Amadís helps defeat her uncle Abiseos,
                     who has usurped Briolanja's throne. Thereafter, Briolanja's fate varies
                     according to the version of the legend one follows. Briolanja falls in love
                     with Amadís, and Montalvo cites five versions of the results. Either Amadís
                     rejects her, Amadís indulges in an affair with her (with Oriana's permission)
                     Briolanja imprisons him until he agrees to have a child with him, he either
                     gives in and Briolanja bears twins, or Briolanja relents and allows Amadís to
                     replace himself with Galaor. In the 1508 Briolanja is the occasion for Oriana's
                     jealousy. The dwarf observes that Amadís admires her beauty and misinterprets
                     the fact that Amadís uses the sword she has given him. Oriana's jealousy is
                     based on what she believes to be good information--the dwarf, Amadís's constant
                     companion, tells her he loves the girl who gave him the sword. Briolanja is
                     represented as quite beautiful, and she places second in the beauty challenges
                     at Ínsola Firme. She marries Galaor in Book IV. In <bibl>Las sergas de
                        Esplandián</bibl>, Montalvo includes praise for Briolanja, saying that she
                     must have been in fact more beautiful than Oriana.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="dwarf">
                  <persName>el enano</persName>
                  <persName>the dwarf</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Amadís's unnamed dwarf is, along with his squire Gandalín, his
                     constant traveling companion. Dwarves appear frequently in chivalric romance,
                     perhaps as the opposite of the giants who are habitual enemies. Amadís's dwarf
                     provides comic relief, and his information is not always sound. He accidentally
                     provokes Oriana's jealousy when he tells her Amadís is in love with
                     Briolanja.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Gandalin">
                  <persName>Gandalín</persName>
                  <persName>Gandalin</persName>
                  <note resp="#set">Gandalín, son of Gandales, is Amadís's foster brother and
                     childhood companion. He accompanies Amadís through all his adventures, serving
                     as squire and messenger. Gandalín is a brave fighter who dispatches
                     non-knightly foes, including the giantess Andandona. He briefly becomes
                     governor of Ínsola Firme, inspiring the Barataria episode of Miguel de
                     Cervantes's <bibl>Don Quixote</bibl>. Eventually Amadís knights him, finds him
                     a wife, and grants him territory on a permanent basis.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Abiseos">
                  <persName>Abiseos</persName>
                  <note resp="#set">Abiseos is Briolanja's uncle. He usurped the kingdom of
                     Sobradisa from his brother. Amadís and company eventually defeat him.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Darasion">
                  <persName>Darasión</persName>
                  <note resp="#set">Darasion is the son of Abiseos, usurper of Briolanja's kingdom
                     of Sobradisa.</note>

               </person>
               <person xml:id="Dramis">
                  <persName>Dramís</persName>
                  <note resp="#set">Dramis is the son of Abiseos, usurper of Briolanja's kingdom of
                     Sobradisa.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Briolanja_aunt">
                  <persName>la dueña</persName>
                  <note resp="#st">Briolanja's unnamed aunt is a cantankerous personality who nearly
                     gets Amadís killed and sends misleading letters in her quest to restore her
                     niece to the throne of Sobradisa.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Galaor">
                  <persName>Galaor</persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Ungan">
                  <persName>Ungan</persName>
                  <persName>Ungan el Picardo</persName>
                  <persName>el maestro</persName>
                  <note>Wisest clergyman in Perion's kingdom and counselor of the king.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Alberto">
                  <persName>Alberto de Campania</persName>
                  <persName>el clérigo</persName>                  
                  <note>Another clergyman, counselor/adviser of Perion.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Anteles">
                  <persName>Anteles</persName>
                  <note>Another clergyman, counselor/adviser of Perion.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="anon">
                  <persName>Squire_1</persName>
                  <note>We are using anon to signify all of the unnamed characters of the Amadís,
                     which include damsels, squires, giants, hermits, knights, ladies, and other
                     minor characters. If characters are distinct without having a name, like <persName ref="#dwarf">the dwarf</persName> or <persName ref="#Damsel_Denmark">the damsel of Denmark</persName>, they have their own xml ids.</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Balays">
                  <persName>Balays de Carsante</persName>
                  <persName>Balays of Carsante</persName>
                  <note resp="#ebb">Balays of Carsante is grateful to Amadis for rescuing him from the dungeon of the magician Arcalaus. He prevents Galaor and Amadis from unwittingly killing each other by revealing their concealed identities.<!--Stacey: you may want to rewrite this one!--></note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </div>
         <div type="fictional_places">
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="Alima">
                  <placeName>Alima</placeName>
                  <note resp="#heb">One of the properties that belongs to King Garinter, where he
                     meets Amadis of Gaul's father for the first time.</note>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="Angaduza">
                  <placeName>Angaduza</placeName>
                  <note resp="#st">Angaduza is a forest (floresta) adjacent to the castle of
                     Briolanja's aunt.</note>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="Antalia">
                  <placeName>Antalia</placeName>
                  <note resp="#heb">Scottish village where Gandales and his family anchor after
                     rescuing Amadis.</note>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="Sobradisa">
                  <placeName>Sobradisa</placeName>
                  <note>Briolanja's kingdom.</note>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="Serolis">
                  <placeName>Sérolis</placeName>
                  <note resp="#heb">Neighboring country of the kingdom of Sobradisa.</note>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </div>
         <div type="geographical_places">
            <listPlace><place xml:id="Paris">
               <placeName>Paris</placeName>
               <note resp="#ebb"><persName ref="#Arthur">King Arthur</persName> is said to have defeated <persName ref="#Floyon">Floyon</persName> in front of the gates of Paris. </note>
            </place>
               <place xml:id="littleBritain">
                  <placeName>Lesser Britain</placeName>
                  <placeName>Little Britain</placeName>
                  <note resp="#ebb"><!--ebb Are these indeed identical?--></note>
               </place>
            
            <place xml:id="Scotland">
               <placeName>Scotland</placeName>
               <note resp="#ebb">The Knight <persName ref="#Gandales">Gandales</persName> carries the infant <persName ref="#Amadis">Amadis</persName> by sea to Scotland, to the town <placeName ref="#Antalia">Antalia</placeName>.</note>
            </place>
               <place xml:id="Windsor">
                  <placeName>Windsor</placeName>
                  <note resp="ebb">Where Amadis says he'll bring Galaor after the two are recovered from their nearly mortal combat. Windsor appears to be the domain of Queen Brisena.</note>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </div>
         <div type="publications">
            <listBibl>

               <bibl xml:id="Munday">
                  <title>The first book of Amadis of Gaule</title>
                  <author>Anthony Munday</author>
                  <pubPlace/>
                  <publisher/>
                  <date when="1590">1590</date>
                  <note resp="#st">Made after Nicholas de Hebreray's French version (Lyon
                     1531)</note>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Hebreray">
                  <title>Amadis de Gaule</title>
                  <author>Nicholas de Hebreray</author>
                  <pubPlace/>
                  <publisher/>
                  <date from="1531" to="1555">1531, 1532
                     <!--st grab date for vols 2, 3, 4 --></date>
                  <note resp="#st">Four volumes published separately in Lyon. First volume Lyon
                     1532.</note>
               </bibl>

            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
