<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="Amadis.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amadis of Gaul, by VASCO LOBEJRA.</title>
            <editor role="translator">Robert Southey</editor>
            <editor>Stacey Triplette</editor>
            <editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor>
            <editor>Helena Bermúdez Sabel</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority ana="printer">Printed by N. Biggs, Cross-court, Fleet-street</authority>
            <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Paternoster Row, London</pubPlace>
            <date>1803</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p><s>Rekeyed from a public domain Google-digitized text via HathiTrust.</s></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" xml:id="S2">
            <head>Chapter 2. <locus from="9" to="16"/></head>
            <p><s>At night when all was husht, <persName ref="#Darioleta">Darioleta</persName> rose, and threw a mantle over her mistress, and they went into the garden.</s><s>When <persName ref="#Helisena">Elisena</persName> came to the chamber door her whole body trembled, and her voice that she could not speak.</s><s><persName ref="#Perion">King Perion</persName> had fallen asleep, he dreamt that some one, he knew not who, entered his chamber by a secret door, who thrusting a hand between his ribs, took out his heart and threw it into the river.</s><s>He asked why that cruelty was committed, and was answered--<milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#anon"/>it is nothing! there is another heart left there which I must take from you, though against my will<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>.</s><s>Then the King suddenly awoke in great fear, and blessed himself.</s><s>At this moment the two damsels had opened the door, and were entering; he heard them, and being full of his dream suspected treason, when he saw a door open behind the hangings, of which he had not known, and leaping from the bed he caught up his sword and shield.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>What is this?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> cried Darioleta.</s><s>The King then knew her, and saw Elisena his beloved; he dropt his shield and sword and throwing a mantle about him which was ready by the bed, he went and embraced her whom he loved.</s><s>Darioleta then took up the sword in token of his promise and oath, and went into the garden, and Perion remained alone with Elisena, in whom as he beheld her by the light of the three torches, he thought all the beauty of the world was<note anchored="true" resp="#Southey">Here, says the Spanish author, we should learn, that when women turn aside their thoughts from worldly things, despising the great beauty with which Nature has endowed them, the fresh youth which so much increases it, and the delights and pleasures which with the riches of their parents they might hope to enjoy, and chuse for the salvation of their souls to place themselves as recluses in poor habitations, and offer up with all obedience their own free will to be subject to others, and pass their time without any of the pleasures or glories of the world, though their sisters and kindred are enjoying them; they ought with great earnestness to stop their ears, and close their eyes, and refuse to see friend or relation, but retiring altogether to devout contemplation and holy prayer, think them the true delights, as indeed they are; lest by seeing and hearing, their religious purposes be overcome, and it should be with them as it was with the Princess Elisena.</note> centered.</s></p>
            
           
            
            <p><s>When it was time that they should part, Darioleta returned to the chamber.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>I know, Lady,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> said she, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>that heretofore you have been better pleased with me than you are now; but we must go, for time calleth us.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>Elisena rose.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>I beseech you,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> said Perion, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>do not forget the place!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> and she departed with the damsel.</s><s>He remained in his room, and recollecting his dream, which still affrighted him, a wish to know its signification made him desirous to return to his own country, where were many wise men skilful in the solution of such things.</s></p>
            
            <p><s>Ten days King Perion sojourned at <placeName ref="#Alima">Alima</placeName>, and every night his beloved mistress visited him.</s><s>Then it was necessary that he should depart, despite of his own inclination, and the tears of Elisena.</s><s>He took leave of <persName ref="#Garinter">Garinter</persName> and the Queen, and having armed himself, when he looked for his sword to gird it on, he missed it; though the loss grieved him, for it was a tried and goodly weapon, he durst not enquire for it, but making his <persName ref="#Squire1">Squire</persName> procure him another, he departed straight for his own kingdom.</s><s>Albeit before his departure Darioleta came and told him of the great affliction and loneliness in which his Lady was left.</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Perion"/>I commend her to you my friend,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> said he, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>as mine own proper heart<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/>; then taking from his finger a ring of two which he wore, each resembling the other, he bade her carry it to his love.</s></p>
            
            <p><s>So Elisena remained, leading a solitary life, and in great grief.</s><s>Darioleta comforted her the best she could, and the time past on, till she felt herself great with child, and lost the appetite for food and the pleasure of sleep, and the fresh colour of her countenance.</s><s>Then was her sorrow and carefulness greater, and not without cause, for in that time was there a law, that any woman, of what quality or estate soever, offending in such sort, could not excuse herself from death.</s><s>This so cruel and abominable a custom endured, till the coming of the good <persName ref="#Arthur">King Arthur</persName>, who was the best King that ever there reigned, and he revoked it at the time when he slew <persName ref="#Floyon">Floyon</persName> in battle, before the gates of <placeName ref="#Paris">Paris</placeName>.</s><s>And albeit because of the words which Perion swore upon his sword, she was without fault before God, yet was she not before the world, for they had been so secret.</s><s>To let him know her condition, was what she could not think, for he was young and proud of heart, and took no delight elsewhere than where renown was to be gained, and so was for ever going an Errant Knight from one place to another.</s><s>So she found no remedy for her life; yet did not the loss of life afflict her so much as that of her dear and beloved Lord.</s><s>But God, by whose permission all this had come to pass for his holy service, gave such discretion to Darioleta, that she remedied all.</s></p>
            
            <p><s>In the palace of King Garinter there was an arched chamber separated from the rest, which overlooked the river; it had a little iron door through which the Damsels sometime were wont to go out by the water side, but now none inhabited the apartment.</s><s>This chamber, by Darioleta’s advice, did Elisena request of her father, as suiting her disposition and solitary life, where she might perform her prayers undisturbed, with no companion but Darioleta, who had always served and accompanied her.</s><s>This request she lightly obtained, and hereupon was the key of the iron door given to Darioleta, to open when it pleased the Princess to recreate herself by the river.</s><s>Here was Elisena somewhat comforted, to find herself in a place so convenient for her purpose, and she required council of her damsel what should be done with the fruit that she travailed withal?</s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>What?<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> replied Darioleta, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>it must suffer to save you.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Helisena"/>Holy Mary,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> then said Elisena, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>shall I consent to destroy the child of him whom I love best in the world?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>Leave alone those thoughts,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> the damsel answered, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>if they kill you they will not spare the infant: it were great folly to destroy yourself and your lover, who could not live after you, for the sake of saving the child, who if you die, must die also.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s></p>
            
            <p><s>As this Damsel was of quick mind herself, and now guided by the grace of God, she determined to have the remedy ready before the need; and it was in this guise: she took four boards and with them made an ark large enough to contain a new born child and its garments, and long enough for the sword, she fastened them together with bitumen in such sort, as the water should have no place to enter.</s><s>She hid all this under her bed till she had compleated it; and it was even and close as if a master had made it.</s><s>Then she showed it to Elisena and asked for what she thought it was designed?</s><s>She answered, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Helisena"/>I know not.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>You shall know,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> said the Damsel, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>when need is.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>Elisena replied, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Helisena"/>but little do I care to know what is done or what is said, for I am near to lose all my joy and comfort.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>Then had Darioleta great grief, and she went apart not bearing to see her mistress weep.</s></p>
            
            <p><s>It was not long before her travail came, and in those new and strange pains, in bitterness of heart, and not daring to cry out or groan, it pleased the Lord that she was safely delivered of a son.</s><s>The Damsel took him in her arms, and saw that the boy was a fair boy had he not been born to hard fortune, but she delayed not to execute what of necessity had been resolved.</s><s>She wrapt him in rich garments, and laying him by his mother brought the ark.</s><s>Elisena cried <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Helisena"/>what will you do?<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s><milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Darioleta"/>Place him here,<milestone unit="said" ana="intStart"/> she answered, <milestone unit="said" ana="intEnd"/>and launch him down the stream, and belike he may escape.<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/></s><s>Then the Mother took him in her arms, and wept bitterly over him.</s><s>But Darioleta took ink and parchment, and wrote upon it,</s> 
               <!--ebb 2015-09-14: We can't wrap a floatingText inside an <s> element in TEI, more's the pity. So I've had to artificially end the sentence here. Can't use a <div> element either.-->
               <floatingText><body><p><s>this is Amadis,<note anchored="true" resp="#Southey">Este es Amadis sin tiempo, hijo de rey; y sin tiempo dezia ella porque creya que luego seria muerto.</note> son of a King.</s></p></body></floatingText>
            
            <s>It was the name of her saint, and of great reverence in that country.</s><s>She covered the parchment with wax, and hung it by a string round the neck of the babe, and Elisena fastened upon the string the ring which King Perion had given her at his departure.</s><s>Darioleta then placed the infant in the ark, and laid his father’s sword beside him; this done, she covered the ark, which was securely joined and calked, and opening the iron door, took it in her arms, and placed it in the river, commending it to God.</s></p>       
            <p><s>The tide ran strong, and soon carried the ark into the sea, which was not more than a half-league distant.</s><s>Now the dawn appeared, and it pleased God that there was a Knight of <placeName ref="#Scotland">Scotland</placeName> sailing on that sea, returning from <placeName ref="#littleBritain">the lesser Britain</placeName> to his country, with his wife, who had newly been delivered of a son called <persName ref="#Gandalin">Gandalin</persName>.</s><s>The morning was both calm and clear, whereby <persName ref="#Gandales">the Knight Gandales</persName> saw the ark floating among the waves, and he ordered the mariners to put out a boat and take it up.</s><s>They speedily overtook it, and Gandales opened the cover, and beholding the babe within he cried, <milestone unit="said" ana="start" resp="#Gandales"/>this is from no mean place!<milestone unit="said" ana="end"/> and this he said because of the rich garments, and the ring and the good sword, and he cursed the mother who had for fear abandoned so fair a child.</s><s>He carefully laid aside all the things that were contained in the ark, and desired his wife to breed up the infant, and she ordered the nurse of her own child Gandalin to suckle him.</s><s>So they went their way through the sea with a favourable time, and took port in a town in Scotland called <placeName ref="#Antalia">Antalia</placeName>, and from thence departing they came to his castle, which was one of the good ones of the land; there he had the child brought up like his own son, and such he was believed to be, because the mariners who took up the ark, had sailed away to other parts.</s></p>
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
