<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../Amadis.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Amadís de Gaula Volumes I-IV</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <p> We have used the text of the <bibl>1547 <title>Amadís</title> (Sevilla: Jacopo
                        Cromberberger)</bibl> from which Southey translated. Images of the 1547 are
                    from the Biblioteca Virtual de Andalucía. This text is very similar to the text
                    of the first extant <bibl>
                        <title>Amadís</title>, the 1508 Jorge Coci edition</bibl>, upon which most
                    modern editions are based. Garci Rodríguez de Montalvo, a regidor or civic
                    official of the city of Medina del Campo, edited and compiled the version of
                    Amadís we know today from one or more medieval originals. The medieval material
                    is concentrated in Books I-III, with occasional asides from the author. Book IV
                    and the prologues are original to Montalvo. Only one fragment of a medieval
                    Amadís exists, but the first texts are thought to be based in part on the
                    Lancelot material in France and likely appeared in Spain in the mid-fourteenth
                    century. Evidence in the form of character names and references in poetry dates
                    to the fourteenth century. The primitive or medieval Amadís is now thought to be
                    Castilian and not Portuguese or French. The attribution to Portuguese knight
                    Vasco de Lobeira is now known to be apocryphal.<ptr
                        target=" http://www.bibliotecavirtualdeandalucia.es/catalogo/catalogo_imagenes/imagen_id.cmd?idImagen=5010234"
                    />
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This digital critical edition seeks to reproduce the reading experience of the
                        <bibl>1547 <title>Amadís de Gaula</title> (Sevilla: Cromberger)</bibl> with
                    which Robert Southey worked for his translation in order to facilitate
                    comparisons. The following modifications have been made to the 1547 print
                    edition. <list rend="numbered">
                        <item>We employ the letters <hi>i/e/u/y/j</hi> as in modern Spanish: i/e/u
                            express vowel sounds and <hi>y/j</hi> express consonants. For example,
                                <mentioned>reyna</mentioned> in the 1547 has been transcribed as
                                <mentioned>reina</mentioned> and <mentioned>cauallero</mentioned> as
                                <mentioned>cavallero</mentioned>. The letter <hi>y</hi> has vocalic
                            value only at the ends of words, as in <mentioned>muy</mentioned> and
                                <mentioned>rey</mentioned>, and as the conjunction meaning
                                <gloss>and</gloss>.</item>
                        <item>We preserve most of the consonant use of the 1547, including the
                            alternation of <hi>b/v</hi> and <hi>m/n</hi> before <hi>b/p</hi> as well
                            as the absence or presence of <hi>h</hi>. We normalize the use of
                                <hi>qu</hi>.</item>
                        <item>Doubled consonants, <hi>bb</hi>, <hi>cc</hi>, <hi>ff</hi>, etc. are
                            resolved as single except where they have phonetic value.</item>
                        <item>The single <hi>r</hi> and not <hi>rr</hi> has been transcribed after
                            consonants: <mentioned>honrra</mentioned> becomes
                                <mentioned>honra</mentioned>. In some cases the <hi>rr</hi> has been
                            supplied for <hi>r</hi> for phonetic reasons:
                                <mentioned>tiera</mentioned> becomes
                            <mentioned>tierra</mentioned>.</item>
                        <item>We resolve the few abbreviations in the 1547 without alerting the
                            reader. For example, <mentioned>q̃</mentioned> has been resolved as
                                <mentioned>que</mentioned> and <mentioned>scta</mentioned> as
                                <mentioned>sancta</mentioned>. Any ambiguities in abbreviations are
                            tagged.</item>
                        <item>We transcribe the tironian sign as <mentioned>y</mentioned>.</item>
                        <item>We use accentuation according to the norms of modern Spanish in order
                            to guide the reader’s pronunciation and to disambiguate words.</item>
                        <item>We use capital and lower-case letters as in modern Spanish in order to
                            clearly mark proper names and the boundaries of sentence-like
                            groups.</item>
                        <item>We normalize the union and separation of words according to modern
                            Spanish usage.</item>
                        <item>We preserve the punctuation of the 1547 in order to facilitate
                            clause-by-clause comparisons with Southey’s translation. We preserve the
                            1547’s clause-like units (the space between successive punctuation
                            marks) even though we recognize significant differences from modern
                            usage. The 1547 uses <hi>. : /</hi> and infrequent <hi>?</hi> as
                            punctuation, and while sentence-like groups end with a period, the
                            period <hi>.</hi> is also used within sentence-like groups to introduce
                            dialogue. The punctuation marks <hi>:</hi> and <hi>/</hi> appear to
                            freely alternate. We reproduce <hi>. : /</hi> as they appear in the 1547
                            without modernization. We have not added modern <hi>¿?</hi> to mark
                            questions. We do not mark dialogue with em dash; rather, for this
                            digital edition, dialogue, including questions, has been coded in the
                            milestone element. We do not preserve the <hi>//</hi> that indicates
                            line breaks in the middle of words. Our goal in these punctuation
                            decisions is to render structural elements of the text at the sentence
                            and clause level as Southey would have confronted them in order to
                            elucidate whether the 1547 structure and punctuation influenced Southey
                            in his own construction of sentences and clauses, which we observe
                            differs from standard English use.</item>
                        <item>Obvious printer errors have been tagged with the sic element.
                            Corrections are provided based on <bibl>Juan Manuel Cacho Blecua’s
                                critical edition (Madrid: Cátedra, 1999)</bibl>, which takes into
                            consideration multiple sixteenth-century editions of <title>Amadís de
                                Gaula</title> including the <bibl>Sevilla 1526</bibl> on which the
                                <bibl>Sevilla 1547</bibl> is based.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="7">

                <head>Capítulo VII <locus from="xlii-r" to="xlv-r"/>
                </head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Cómo al tercero día el Donzel del Mar se partió de la corte del rey
                        Languines: vinieron aquellos tres cvalleros que traían un cavallero en unas
                        andas y a su muger alevosa.</p>
                </argument>
                <p> Al tercero día que el Donzel del Mar se partió de casa del rey Languines donde
                    fue armado cavallero llegaron aí los tres cavalleros que llevavan la dueña
                    falsa: y al cavallero su marido mal llagdo en unas andas: y los tres cavalleros
                    pusieron en la mano del rey la dueña de parte de un cavallero novel: y
                    contáronle quanto del aviniera. El rey se santiguó muchas vezes en oir tal
                    traició muger y a gradeció mucho al cavallero que la embiara que ninguno no
                    sabía que el Donzel del Mar era cavallero: sino su señora Oriana y las otras que
                    ya oístes: antes cuidavan que era ido a vera a su amo Gandales. El rey dixo al
                    cavallero de las andas. Tan alevosa muger como es la vuestra non deve biuir.
                    Señor dixo él vos hazed lo que devéis: mas yo nunca consentiré matar la cosa del
                    mundo que más amo: y despedido del rey se hizo llevar en sus andas. El rey dixo
                    a la dueña: por dios mas leal vos es aquel cavallero que vos a él: mas yo haré
                    que compréis vuestra deslealtad: y mandóla quemar. El rey se maravilló mucho
                    quién sería el cavallero que allí los hiziera venir: y dixo el escudero: con
                    quien el Donzel del Mar se aposentara en su castillo: por ventura si será un
                    cavallero novel que aguardamos yo y una donzella de denmarcha que oy aquí llegó.
                    Y que cavallero es dixo el rey. Señor dixo el escudero él es muy niño y tan
                    hermoso que es maravilla de lo ver y vile hazer tanto en armas en poca debora:
                    que si ha ventura de biuir será el mejor cavallero del mundo. Entonces contó
                    quanto del viera: y como librara al rey Perión de muerte sabéis vos dixo el rey
                    cómo ha nombre: no señor dixo él: que él se encubre mucho en demasia entonces
                    ovo el rey y todos mas gana de lo saber que ante: y el escudero dixo: la
                    donzella anduvo mas con el que no yo. Es aquella donzella dixo el rey: si dixo
                    él que venía a demandar la hija del rey Lisuarte. Luego mandó que ante él
                    viniesse y contó quanto del viera: y como la aguardara por lo que la donzella
                    que le dio la lança dixo: que la traía para el mejor cavallo que agora la podría
                    en mano tener: tanto sé yo del dixo ella: mas de su nombre no sé nada. Ay dios
                    quién sería dixo el rey: mas su amiga no dudava quien podría ser: porque la
                    donzella le avía contado como la venía a demandar para llevar consigo. Y assí
                    como se lo nombró: sintió en sí gran alteración porque creido tuvo que el rey
                    daría lugar que la llevassen a su padre: y ida no sabría nuevas tan contino de
                    aquella que mas que a si misma quería. Assí passaron seis días que del no
                    supieron nuevas. Y estando el rey hablando con su hijo Agrajes ue se quería
                    partir a GSaula con su compaña entró una donzella por la puerta: y finco los
                    inojos ante ellos: y dixo. Señor oídme un oco ante vuestro padre. Entonces tomó
                    un sus manos un yelmo con tantas heridas de espada: que ninugn lugar sano en él
                    avía: y diolo a Agrajes y dixo. Señor tomad este yelmo en lugar de la cabeça de
                    Galpano: y do os lo de parte de un cavallero novel: aquel a quein mas conviene
                    traer armas que a otro cavallero que en el mundo sea y este yelmo vos embia él:
                    porque deshonrró una donzella que iva en vuestro mandado. Como dixo el muerto es
                    Galpano por mano de un cavallero: Por Dios donzella maravilias me dezis. Cierto
                    señor dixo ella aquella conquirió y mató quantos avía en su castillo y a la fin
                    se combatió con él solo y y cortóle la cabeça: y por ser eonjosa de traer me
                    dixo que bastava el yelmo. Cierto dixo el rey aquel es el cavallero novel que
                    por aquí passó que por cierto sus cavallerías estrañas son de otras/ y preguntó
                    a la donzella: si sabía como avia noche. Si señor dixo ella: mas esto fue con
                    gran arte. Por Dios dezídmelo dixo el rey que mucho me haréis alegre. Sabed
                    señor dixo ella que ha bombre el Donzel del Mar. Quando esto oyó el rey fue
                    maravillado y todos los otros y dixo. Si él fue demandar quien lo hiziesse
                    cavallero: no deve ser culpado/que mucho ha que me lo rogó; y yo lo tardé y hize
                    ma de tardar cavallería a quien ella tan bien obra. Ay dixo Agrajes donde le
                    podría hallar. Él se vos encomienda mucho dixo la donzella: y mandvaos dezir por
                    mi que lo hallaréis en la guerra de Gaula si aí fuerdes. Ay dios que buenas
                    nuevas me dezi dixo Agrajes: agora he más talante de me ir: y si lo yo hallo
                    nunca a mi grado del seré partido. Derecho es dixo la donzella que él mucho os
                    ama. Grande fue el alegría que todos ovieron de las buenas nuevas del Donzel del
                    Mar. Mas sobre todos fue la de su señora Oriana aunque mas que ninguno lo
                    encubría. El rey quiso saber de las donzellas/ por qual manera lo hizieron
                    cavallero: y ellas selo contaron todo. Y dixo: mas cortesía halló en vos que en
                    mí: pues yo no lo tardava sino por su por que lo vía muy moço. La donzella contó
                    a Agrajes el mandado que le traía de aquella que la historía contara adelante. Y
                    él se partió con muy buena compaña para Gaula. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
